So in 2009, a
lot of people were telling me the idea of continuous delivery was crazy.
And I feel we're in kind of the same thing right now with a dark factory.
It will not work here.
That's what I keep hearing over and over again.
But what they're actually signaling to me, we're not ready yet.
So it's not the technology that can't make it work.
It's not something
they want to be able to do eventually, but they're just not set up for this.
Oh, no. Oh!
Well, welcome.
Last day.
I guess that's what happens.
I'm going to talk to you.
Maybe not on the technical side, but more on the organizational side.
So if you here for any technology, you can still leave
if you want to.
So in 2009,
a lot of people were telling me the idea of continuous delivery was crazy.
And I feel we're in kind of the same era
or kind of the same thing right now with a dark factory.
It will not work here.
That's what I keep hearing over and over again.
But what they're actually signaling to me, we're not ready yet.
So it's not the technology that can't make it work.
It's not something
they want to be able to do eventually, but they're just not set up for this.
And there's been a lot of conference talks here
about optimizing the agents with loops and harnesses and all those pieces.
And I think that's great.
But eventually we'll all get there, right?
It's not that this is the rocket science.
And yes, we'll have to assemble this in a good way.
But one day this will kind of become commodity
somewhere, maybe even going into one of the, you know, frontier
labs that just offers this as a service and we'll kind of make this work.
And that's not going to be the differentiator for your organization.
So I'm starting from there
I assume we're heading towards a dark factory,
some kind of form of autonomous working within an organization.
What I've seen for the people
adopting this within organization, including here where I work at Tessl,
it changes dynamic of the way you collaborate around this.
And for those familiar, there's like Conway's Law,
like the way you organize yourselves and the tools.
There is a relationship on how they interact and kind of work
together on this.
But today I'm not talking about like how you become better with your agent,
but it is about how will we'll change your team
dynamics, Your platform and your organization.
So that's what I'll take you through.
Enabling the team.
I assume most of you somewhere work in a team
and that you're not somewhere a solo practitioner working.
So it kind of works different than just you with your Claude Code and a team
working together around that with Claude or any of the coding agents
there as well.
The narrative that I heard a lot
is, well, the developer eventually becomes more of a conductor
and an orchestrator of agents, and I think that's fair.
That's been an evolution that we're on, on the path.
We're more like
becoming the managers of the agents and kind of dealing with the agents.
Now, what I've seen is that if eventually
a lot of developers told me we didn't sign up for this,
we didn't sign up for better prompting, writing better specs.
We're engineers, we're technical, and that creates friction.
Like, is this the role that we really want to do?
There was a thing that came around, which maybe is more context engineering
that put a first step around like, hey, it's not just a prompt.
Well, test the prompt.
We'll kind of evaluate the prompt.
We'll kind of distribute the prompt and kind of optimize the prompt.
So yes, there's a little bit of engineering,
but still a lot of developers kind of felt empty just working
kind of with a prompt and a specification as such.
What I've seen
is that when we started introducing harness and loops
and eventually more autonomous work within the whole organization,
a new technical path opened.
All of a sudden we were helping the agent with tooling,
building tooling for the agent, and that kind of reignited
some of the developers who kind of felt that it wasn't for them.
Now all of a sudden they were like, yes, we can do this.
We have that knowledge.
We're like, somehow helping this even with a kind of programmatic way.
So I think that's interesting that the identity where we say
abstraction, abstraction, abstraction, technically, all of a sudden
the craft created some new location for more engineering stuff to go to.
Now, when I get the question,
can we please help people and their skeptical people?
What did I do?
And I always say that these are really great people
to engage in
creating better context for the agent because you tell them, please improve.
Please put all your knowledge to improve the result of the agent
and the same with the harness.
So if you have those kind of more resistant people that like complain
maybe about the quality that things were produced by
just the vanilla kind of coding agent use almost
that anger use, kind of that skepticism to kind of make it better.
And the big mentality shift,
if I would advise a company right now
for their developers, is kind of stop fixing the code
that the agent kind of produced, but improve the system.
I'm not
the only one saying this in this event, but kind of that is the difference.
Like you kind of improve the system.
And I think it was a couple of years you said it
like, stop building the thing, but build the thing that builds the thing, right?
So we going on that abstraction where that is with context, with harness,
with loops, and that is kind of the change that a lot of people
who are still very tightly in the loop, auto completion, prompting
that they kind of need to think about elevating this
to the system, thinking. So
what we're
really trying to do is minimize the human touches,
but still with good engineering practices and some of the narrative
that comes up more often in the beginning, we're like,
oh, great vibe coding a prompt, and it gives a result
and we can keep going where we now see, well, we're
kind of instructing it through prompts, but we're also instructing this like,
please do it with tests, please update the documentation, please do this.
All the things that were saying to good engineers,
we're now asking the agent to do so.
If you still have people who kind of YOLO their way into this,
I think you should tell them, no, stop doing this.
Like engineering practices still matter for you to maintain
the system and also for the agent to keep getting better at this.
What I started seeing in some of the more advanced
kind of teams is that they're rituals of, hey, we're doing a planning
and we're doing a retro in a team that they weren't about like, hey,
we had issues with the code, but we're seeing we had issues with the system.
So on the retro part is like, hey,
the agent went over and over hit this problem.
Can we fix the system?
That's something you learn in the retro.
And on the planning side, what I started seeing is that things
that were sufficiently scoped enough
were easy to pick up by agents, because there were well-defined,
and what still was left for the humans were the things that weren't
scoped out well.
So they were like a split in the planning were say, these things can straight
go into agents well defined and the harness is getting better.
And this is conversational things that we need to decide as a team.
And what I find
important is there's a certain kind of cycle that developers go to.
Yes, they learn first about prompting.
They get better specs, context harness, loop.
Also the industry's learning like that.
But there is the lead of the team can say,
well, stop prompting, make the context reusable.
Now we got that.
Now we jump to the next.
So part of the team lead is putting that pace at almost that constraint.
And the directive in the team were it doesn't work where you just say,
go figure it out and do something on your own.
And one of the impacts of that
is that if you start producing as a team more
the people downstream, GTM
people like that, they have a hard time keeping up.
Even users have a hard time keeping up, so you need to help them also
with automation so your harness doesn't stop at your coding.
It also is extended to those people as well.
And the same thing with kind of requiring like gathering requirements.
The input might not come fast enough for your team.
So that's another kind of piece that you need to tap into that workflow as well.
There's a lot of metrics that people are saying
like, hey, is your tokens spend and all that stuff.
I started to believe in these two metrics
to kind of see on how to be more productive.
One is you start measuring how many human touches you still do
to have the agent do the right thing that's supposed to go down.
The better
your harness is, the better your context is, the better your guidelines are.
And on the other hand,
if you're going from solo
to shared system, that becomes a multiplier.
You fix something once everybody gets the benefit.
This is not the multiplier from the one person becoming the ten
x person, but the one change that optimized
the agents has an impact on all the people.
So that is kind of the part that we're all you can start that in a team
working together within your repo, sharing the context, working on a harness.
But what you basically want to do is you want to scale this out.
So we come into the realm of the platform people, right?
Because they're the typical shared organization
working on this now, the platform people, they might not be paying close attention
because there are like infrastructure
and cloud and working on an MCP gateway and stuff like that.
But there's new things like bubbling up there
they need to think about, like maybe skill registries or eval systems for a context
and guardrails specifically for coding agents and identities and stuff.
So they need maybe a little bit of a hand kind of growing to that role and
that kind of central role.
It's hard.
You need an owner to drive that program.
But is it a platform team is a developer experience team.
They don't typically own any of those pieces of the infrastructure,
and the other people don't really do the development.
So there's somewhere a blend.
But you need to kind of make sure that there's an owner driving
this centralized piece and not just within your team,
because you won't have paved roads.
And that's how I see it.
Reusable context across teams, why we're
all inventing how we do the authentication system, right.
This is a shared component.
Let's put it in the registry.
Why building all your harnesses?
Well, if we're all using the same winters and the same security tools, that's
a reusable component.
So I think that will centralize similar to the paved path
for cloud into that platform registry of reuse.
But if everybody can put
stuff like on the internet in the repo, it becomes a sprawl
and it becomes a thing like, well, here's a skill is maintaining it.
That person also has a similar skill and forked it.
Now what I do like, which one do I pick?
So there is a kind of thing that you say there's an owner for this area
and they also care about making it testable.
They make sure that it's modular, that other people can extend
kind of the context, for example, or the harness that is security scant.
So you build kind of a more centralized.
And the fact that it's secured and kind of maintained as something
instead of just something I share around in my organization.
Now, that consensus is hard.
I'm not saying this is tabs versus spaces, but at times it feels like that.
If you have two developer teams having to have consensus on
how the way they work, that requires a lot of communication and brokerage.
So you probably don't end up with one thing, but
a catalog of three four paved roads where they can pick off
and they can still do their own, but that's on their own budget, right?
The centralized pieces will be maintained, and that is supposed to be
the easy way of adoption to go there.
Now, if they do this blindly,
we also want to make sure that they know what it costs.
Because if a visualize the cost,
they might be eager to do some optimization in there.
And that kind of is part of the platform team is making that visible.
How much is it spending?
How much is that kind of helping?
If I can reduce the number of iterations the agent has to run through,
that is an optimization that I can run.
But if I don't visualize that and I just see the end result,
then we don't know, right?
So that is part of the platform team helping people.
And so what I'm arguing is that
we should somewhere move from the solar developer
to the team, shared kind of context and pieces to a multiplayer system
in the organization.
And I think that's where the multiplication effect will happen.
Right?
Because you have this flywheel of improvements to go into multiple directions.
Now, one layer
higher, the VP engineering says, how do I enable the organization?
Right.
And that is that I can predict the story in your organization
hackathon or lunch and learn. Let's share the successes.
Have a shared Slack channel, have a champions program.
That's all generic transformation.
It could have been agile that transformed like that.
It could have been DevOps. It doesn't matter.
And on the other side, we know that the strategy of just,
you know, give licensing and educate people, do something.
Let a thousand flowers bloom.
It doesn't work.
So what I'm advocating is that the kind of on the organizational is that you
give the team leads and the platform that mandate to start doing that work.
And it's not a solo developer piece.
Now, finding people that help
you externally is a mess.
Yes, we have all the titles, the new job
titles, AI product engineer, forward deployed engineer.
There was a whole talk on this, agentic engineer, AI engineer.
It doesn't mean anything.
You cannot judge where what kind of the
maturity of this, because nobody's really that mature.
But it's a signal when you put a job posting out there that people might,
with the new intentional, be looking there,
but it's not a validation of the skills as such.
Right.
So that is challenging for people
kind of hiring people.
Now they come to the interview
and I heard stories about people using
AI to like in their ears,
be response to the interview person and stuff like that.
I think what I hear from most companies is I say, first step is
we give them an exercise and we want them
to really go nuts on the AI to solve this.
You know, if they have help from AI, that's all good.
That shows you kind of like how much they can kind
of leverage the AI to do this.
Now, after they pass this, you do a walkthrough
and you actually say, please explain me what happened.
Why is this a good idea?
That's where you are testing the tests and the engineering skills
on why they doing this.
First part AI, then engineering.
And this third thing is how do you collaborate?
Are you willing to share?
Are you open or are you a solo player.
That's another signal that you tap into, right?
But that fits into that whole thing of like making it shareable,
making it reusable, making it engineering grade within an organization.
Those are the people that you look for, not people who've studied ML or AI,
not people who are like experts per se at decoding.
There's a blend on this.
Now, you might not find a person who has all three, which is okay,
but at least, you know, like, hey, they're very savvy on this piece.
But then for the other piece, they need mentoring and they need tutoring, but
like, don't put all the three pieces into one kind of saying,
like they're junior or senior.
They have different skills on their
now the VP engineering has to defend this
and they have to make the case right.
Well we are X amount of licenses that we solve.
We have faster delivery.
Maybe they can promise but hard to prove we have quality that improved.
Again hard to say, but similar to what I said
with the metrics of how effective are your agents, you can show that
how much turns and how much improvement that you're making on that journey.
And same thing how much does is reuse.
So it's an easier way to kind of show metrics than comparing productivity
with and without agent coding that help
you in kind of those discussions as well.
And so when people say defenders
are charging completely nuts, so we're going to limit the spend.
You shouldn't say like let's limit all the spends.
Your reflex should be let's optimize the spend and help them
kind of reduce that in a good way, whether that's as simple as saying
pick the right model, educate them on the model,
but also on
giving them better context and harnesses because that will make your cost
go down there as well.
The debate on smaller, ambiguous teams.
Yes, it's nice to have like one person who can do it all.
That's the ultimate dream.
They can do everything.
Typically they're paired with a complementary skill, maybe PM design
and so on.
Okay, then we need a backup if one of them is on holiday.
So that amounts back to three.
And then maybe somebody has to care about production and tickets coming in.
Could be the same people if you're really productive.
But yeah you lose speed on features if you're still doing bugs.
And that depends a little bit on your quality.
And then there's the junior.
You want to get on the road as well
to kind of make sure they're still learning
what good looks like in one of those three areas.
So I think we're still limited in the way in an organization
that we're not going to each team being a solo or 1 or 2.
Yes, a lot of experience, but I think that is the thing now
we keep investing in actually education for that piece as well.
So one of the five things is The Dark Factory.
It's probably a dim factory.
You have to see what risk you're willing to take for what features.
So not all features will become autonomous, but you can invest
more in auditing like provenance, like who changed the code?
Verifiers that kind of check whether
that code was useful.
And when it fails, you invest in situational awareness as well.
So there's a whole spectrum from being a micromanager to being on
a autonomous approval, that everything kind of is correct,
but you make the decision on what your risk level is.
And I think your mode is capturing the knowledge,
right, the knowledge you're putting now into skills in your context
and maybe in your harness, the way you restrain this, your business context.
And for me, that kind of brings continuous delivery actually
to continuous learning.
And if you ask the question how fast can we swap in, swap out something new.
That's your reactive mode.
And if you can improve that, ultimately it's not about making the whole system
more reliable.
But can I keep it reliable while changing more of the system?
I'm working on a website that kind of
where I try to list some of the agent enablement patterns that I described.
I couldn't list them all within this time.
Tell me what you're missing.
I'm trying to source social kind of stories,
so if you have a story how things are going in your organization,
please tell me.
And I'm happy to put on a link in there as well.
And if you're interested in kind of the slides, happy to share those.
And I think if there's one takeaway, it's not the solo player
that will win the game.
It's kind of like at the different levels, how we improve organizations.
Thank you for very much for listening and I hope it was useful.
Oh, no. Oh!